Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Records UA090
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Records
1981 -- 2020
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning
UA090
4 Linear Feet 5 boxes
1 Web sites
145 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: Annual reports; Web crawls; Master's program field project reports; and Additional accessions.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes annual reports and programs generated by the Department of Urban and Environmental Policy; field project reports from the Master's program; and archived versions of the departmental webpage. Additional UEP records are contained within the records of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning has experienced three stages of development. It began in 1973 as a fledgling interdisciplinary program called the Program in Urban, Social and Environmental Policy (PUSEP) situated within the Political Science Department in the School of Arts, Science and Engineering at Tufts University. In 1980 PUSEP was elevated to departmental status and became the Department of Urban and Environmental Policy (UEP) and in 2000 the department's name was changed to reflect its growing orientation to the field of planning. In 2004 UEP became an accredited planning program, with that designation granted by the Planning Accreditation Board (PAB). PAB is comprised of three separate organizations: the American Planning Association, the Association of Collegiate Schools of Planning, and the American Institute of Certified Planners. The founder of the original program was the visionary planner-architect Hermann H. Field. Mr. Field had a distinguished career in urban planning before he envisioned a new master's degree program that responded to the needs of urban development, land use planning, architectural design, as well as social and environmental concerns.
Mr. Field was born in Zurich, Switzerland. He graduated from Harvard College, the Harvard Graduate School of Design, and the Swiss Federal Polytechnic Institute. He directed the urban development of Cleveland College before becoming planning director at the Tufts School of Medicine from 1961 through 1972. social, urban or rural, local or global. Accordingly, your curriculum focus can be narrower (on the public policy and planning challenges in one' policy or planning area) or broader (on sustainable development which looks at these issues as a whole), depending on your goals.
In 1972 Mr. Field taught a pathbreaking course in environmental planning and design at Tufts and developed the framework for a new master's program, which enrolled its first class in 1973. He taught and directed the program until his retirement in 1978. Mr. Field continued to provide guidance and vision to the program until his death at age 90 in 2001. He wrote in 1982 in the 50th anniversary report of his class at Harvard: "I was appalled by the mindless despoiling of the physical environment essential to any quality of life, urban or otherwise, in which my profession was a key participant." Mr. Field's vision of higher education for planners and policy makers embodied a holistic view of planning encompassing a sensitivity to community participation, social justice, and environmental concerns. This is the legacy that he has brought to Tufts and to UEP. Shortly before his death he was named a Fellow of the American Institute of Certified Planners.
Through the generous contributions of the friends and family of Hermann Field, the Hermann and Kate Field Education Fund was established to enhance the education goals of UEP.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs
- Department of Urban and Environmental Policy, annual reports, 1988 -- 1997; UA090.001; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes annual reports generated by the Department of Urban and Environmental Policy. Additional UEP records are contained within the records of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Annual reports, 1988 -- 1989; UA090.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1990 -- 1991; UA090.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1992 -- 1993; UA090.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1993 -- 1994; UA090.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1995 -- 1996; UA090.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1996 -- 1997; UA090.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
- Web crawls, 2015 -- 2020; UA090.002; 1 Web sites
  Quarterly web crawls of the Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning website crawled by DCA, as part of the Student Organizations web collection, to document the presesence of Tufts University student organizations on the web.
  Other Finding Aids
  To see all of websites crawled as part of the Student Organizations web collection, please visit https://archive-it.org/collections/6387
  - Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning, 2015 -- 2020; UA090.002.00001; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning, Tufts University
    General
    Frequency: quarterly crawl.
- Master's program field project reports, 1981 -- 2020; UA090.003; 145 Digital Object(s); 3 Linear Feet
  Related Materials
  Some Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning master's program field reports are also Tufts Institute of the Environment (TIE) "Water: Systems, Science and Society" practicums. Please see the UA056,
  Tufts Institute of the Environment Records
  , finding aid for other related materials.
  This series contains Master's program field project reports, accessed via the Tufts Digital Library.
  This series is open for research.
  - Master's program field project reports, 1981 -- 2020; UA090.003.00001
  - Chemical Contamination of Water: The Case of Acton, Massachusetts, 1981; UA090.003.001.00001; Ciccio, Robin; Conant, Stephen A.; Cooke, Cheryl; Evans, James J.; Gold, Howard M.; Henderson, Kathryn F.; Lewis, John R.; Loconte, John L.; Lyons, Mark L.; Mahoney, Richard B.; Murphy, Christy A.; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 6 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1986 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client:
    Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning
  - Trash to Ash: Incineration of Municipal Waste at the RESCO Waste-to-Energy Facility in Saugus, Massachusetts, 1987; UA090.003.001.00002; Holsinger, Jean; Kleckner, Dave; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1981 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Saugus Action Volunteers for the Environment (SAVE).
  - Right to Know in Massachusetts: Three Years Later…, 1987; UA090.003.001.00003; Friedman, Naomi; Helmick, Jennifer; Madison, Maria; Stein, Linda; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1987 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: The Massachusetts Coalition for Occupational Safety and Health
  - Bridging the Gap: A Workbook on Developing Transitional Housing for Women, 1987; UA090.003.001.00004; Cronin, Mary; DiMatteo, Susan; Lamatie, Sarah; Lindenthal, Jan; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1987 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Women's Institute for Housing and Economic Development
  - Notes on Social Forestry, 1987; UA090.003.001.00005; Geyer, Elaine T.; James, Lisa; Mitropoulos, Antonis; Amrhein, Paul; Clapp, Ros; George, Jacob; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1987 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Coolidge Center for Environmental Leadership
  - Grey Areas: CDCs, Integration and State Policy, 1987; UA090.003.001.00006; Bove, Eric; Brown, Phillip; Hollands, Peter; Snow, Sarah; Thoma, John; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1987 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Association of Community Development Corporations
  - A Window on the Future: The Potential for Residential Growth in Ipswich, Massachusetts, 1988; UA090.003.001.00007; Clark, Barbara; Maffei, Maria; Nichols, Henry; Spriggs, Marshall; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1988 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Town of Ipswich, Massachusetts
  - Community Voices: Profile of Land Use & Development Struggles in Six Boston Neighborhoods, 1988; UA090.003.001.00008; Chen, Yunduo; Isbitsky, Holly; Mapes, Deborah; Roe, Amanda; Warman, Kim; Whiston, Carolyn; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 5 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1988 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Coalition for Community Control of Development
  - Healthy Homes-Healthy Families: A Resource Guide on Housing-Related Health Problems, 1988; UA090.003.001.00009; Alper, Matthew; Farren, Marie; Granfield, Caroline; Reynolds, Lynn; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1988 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: City Life/Vida Urbana
  - Certified: A Citizen's Step-by-step Guide to Certifying Vernal Pools, 1988; UA090.003.001.00010; Burkholder, Rex; Feral, Christie; Clark, Frances; Windmiller, Bryan; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 10)
    1988 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Audubon Society
  - Community Voices: Profile of Land Use & Development Struggles in Six Boston Neighborhoods, 1988; UA090.003.001.00011; Chen, Yunduo; Isbitsky, Holly; Mapes, Deborah; Roe, Amanda; Warman, Kim; Whiston, Carolyn; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 6 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Packaging Waste: An Analysis of H. 1172, 1989; UA090.003.001.00012; Askin, Nancy; Chhetri, Deepak; Geller, Roger; Jacqz, Christian; Rossi, Mark; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 6 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Representative Mark Roosevelt
  - Working the Bugs Out: Improving Pest Control in Public Housing, 1989; UA090.003.001.00013; Greene, Terry; Raphael, Andrea; Schloss, Mary Ellen; Steinberg, Leah; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 13)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Audubon Society
  - Building Our Communities: Unions and Affordable Housing, 1989; UA090.003.001.00014; Alper, Ian; Feighan, Alison; Hahn, Martin; Ziebel, Lisa; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 14)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Trade Union Housing Corporation of the North Shore
  - Boston's Hidden Risk: Highway Transport of Hazardous Materials, 1989; UA090.003.001.00015; Galan-s, Francisco Alberto; Grant, Charles; Hust, Carol; Smith, Mark Petschek; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 15)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: New England Chapter of the Sierra Club
  - The State of the Ark: Preserving Local Lands for Wildlife Habitat, 1989; UA090.003.001.00016; Creighton, Sarah Hammond; Diehl, Kevin; Moss, Joyce G.; Moura, Stephanie; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Department of Fisheries and Wildlife and the New England Aquarium
  - Neighborhood at Work: Meeting Local Needs with Local Resources in Jackson Square, 1989; UA090.003.001.00017; Bashevkin, Joel; Locke, Gretchen; Newman, Neal; Wallace, Kenny; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 5 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Jackson Square Development Collaborative (JSDC)
  - Home Rule or No Rule? Coastal Zone Governance on Massachusetts' North Shore, 1989; UA090.003.001.00018; Ballash, Betsey; Cote, Mel; Hurst, Amy; Sonnenreich, Peter; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 18)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Bay Marine Studies Consortium
  - Affirming Community: Self-Definition and Citizen Participation in East Boston and Charlestown, 1989; UA090.003.001.00019; Bristel, Nancy; Fernandez, Jose; Hoekman, Scott; Schechter, Gail; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 19)
    1989 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Coalition for Community Control of Development
  - Grassroots International: Bringing Our Efforts Home, 1990; UA090.003.001.00020; Swart, Wendy; Wang, Lina; Yuska, Tom; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 20)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Grassroots International
  - Rhode Island Coastal Plain Bioreserve Field Project, 1990; UA090.003.001.00021; Lally, Jody; Lamb, Rhett; Seybolt, Susan; Strickland, John; Woodhouse, Sarah; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: The Nature Conservatory
  - The Public Realm Forum, 1990; UA090.003.001.00022; Baily, Jennifer; Roby, Jennifer; Smyth, Sally; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 22)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Boston GreenSpace Alliance, Inc.
  - Somerville Recycling: A Look to the Future, 1990; UA090.003.001.00023; Allison, Peter; Bissetta, Joanne; Grant, Janet; Norton, Susan; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 23)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: City of Somerville
  - Assessing Human Needs: A Report to the Dudley Street Neighborhood Initiative, 1990; UA090.003.001.00024; Blumenstock, Ceil; Briscoe, Kim; Buxbaum, Laura; Elwood, Paul; Vosseler, Bryan; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 24)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Dudley Street Neighborhood Initiative
  - Pick Your Fight! Environmental Advocacy Case Study, Polonoroeste Project--Brazil, 1990; UA090.003.001.00025; Henderson, Tony; Maldonado, Victor; Munera, Alfredo; Pronove, Gao; Purnomo, Agus; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 25)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: The Coolidge Center
  - "I Thought It Was An Air Vent": A Look at Public Art and Transportation in Boston, 1990; UA090.003.001.00026; Dietrich, Eric; Gage, Mary; Johansen, Jill; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 26)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: UrbanArts
  - Massachusetts Pesticide Amnesty Day, 1990; UA090.003.001.00027; Gittelman, Dena; Julien, Rhona; Lamante, Tom; Yamagata, Masaki; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 27)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Audubon Society
  - Citizen Participation and Referenda: The Massachusetts Local Aid Crisis, 1990; UA090.003.001.00028; Cunningham, Laura; Payton, David; Shimkus, Todd; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 28)
    1990 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client:
  - Mitigation: Reducing the Impacts of the Boston Harbor Project, 1990; UA090.003.001.00029; Bishko, Sherry; Hickey, Colleen; Kahn, Lisa; Lyon, Susan; Schanzle, J. Anthony; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 29)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Massachusetts Water Resources Authority
  - Getting There: Strategies for Inter-City Air and Rail Travel in the Northeast, 1991; UA090.003.001.00030; Conant, Alison; Edmondson, Lucy; Gotelli, Ilze; Redfield, Anne; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 30)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Conservation Law Foundation
  - Grove Hall and Codman Square: Challenges for Commercial Revitalization, 1991; UA090.003.001.00031; Auster, Lucy; Hersh, Bob; Hertz, Tom; Tyson, Herb; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 31)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: City of Boston, Public Facilities Department, Neighborhood Enterprise Division
  - Settling Land Use Disputes: A Guide to Implementing Facilitation & Mediation in Local Zoning Procedures, 1991; UA090.003.001.00032; Gandarilla, Enrique; Matheny, Rebecca; Nordstrom, Rolf; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 32)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client:
  - Opening to Door to Greywater Reuse in Massachusetts, 1991; UA090.003.001.00033; Ganly, Caroline; Greenbaum, James; Marran, Michael; Snyder, Robin; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 33)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Center for Environmental Management
  - Massachusetts River Protection Act: Positive & Negative: What are the Implications?, 1991; UA090.003.001.00034; Glavan, Harrison; McMahon, Susan; Murin, Susan; Suput, Dorothy; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 34)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Grafton, Massachusetts
  - Informational Overview on Fourteen of Boston's Neighborhood Organizations, 1991; UA090.003.001.00035; Chase, Robin; Clifton, Broia; Mansfield, Patricia; Walton, Troy; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 0 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 35)
    1991 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Coalition for Community Control of Development
  - Landscape Management Recommendations for Virginia Road and its Historic Buildings--Minute Man National Park, 1992; UA090.003.001.00036; Cubell, Layne; Deignan, William; Greenough, Katherine; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 5 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 36)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: National Park Service, Concord, MA
  - Screening Mammography: What the Cancer Establishment Never Told You, 1992; UA090.003.001.00037; Dempsey, Kate; Katz, Nechama; Sawyers, Traci; Taggart, Ellen; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 6 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 37)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Women's Community Cancer Project
  - In the Trash Down the Drain: An Inner City Action Guide for Toxics Control, 1992; UA090.003.001.00038; Brengle, Andrew; Rougvie, Carol; Steece, Jane; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 38)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Hispanic Office of Planning and Evaluation
  - New View Neighborhood Development: A Site Plan, 1992; UA090.003.001.00039; Hankamer, Joanna; Ferroggiarao, Karen; Matthews, Meighan; Kaplan, Kate Atkinson; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 39)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: New View Neighborhood Development Corporation
  - The Sibmm Incubator: Sevastopol International Base for Marine Management, 1992; UA090.003.001.00040; Guidi, Daniele; Rhines, Linda; Shakis, Kimberly; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 40)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: American Ukrainian Trade Council
  - Protecting a River: A Volunteer's Guide to the Ipswich River Conservation Strategy, 1992; UA090.003.001.00041; Blatt, Julia; Goodman, Nancy; Ryder, Priscilla; VanLuven, David; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 3 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 41)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Ipswich River Watershed Association
  - The Women's Economic Development Project: Microenterprise Loan Fund, 1992; UA090.003.001.00042; Brown, Monica; Duncan, Christina; Garshick, Rachel; Small, Margaret Somer; Wu, Marilyn; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 42)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Women for Economic Justice
  - A Walk Through the FDIC: A Report on the FDIC's Disposition Process, 1992; UA090.003.001.00043; Flanagan, Anne; Gerber, Joyce; Singer, Joanne; White, Ken; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 43)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Citizens' Housing and Planning Association (CHAPA)
  - From Political Influence to Grassroots Action for Sustainable Development: The History and Future of the New England Coalition for UNCED, 1992; UA090.003.001.00044; Gabriel, Nancy; Jeferiss, Paul; Kieffer, Karen; Schaefer, Barbara; Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning; 1 Digital Object(s); 4 Megabytes (Box 1, Folder 44)
    1992 M.A. in Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Field Project. Client: Coolidge Center for Environmental Leadership